website: www.morajohnsonlaw.ca

Mora Johnson is an international lawyer and consultant focussing on responsible business conduct, bringing over 20 years' experience in international, government, private and non-profit sectors. Mora's areas of expertise include anti-corruption and anti-money laundering, implementation of the UN Guiding Principles on Business and Human Rights including human rights due diligence and supply chain due diligence. Mora is fluent in French and English.

RELEVANT PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE:

2016 - present: Lawyer & Consultant

Provides advice, analysis, research and reporting to a wide diversity of clients including business owners, large corporations, governments, NGOs and international organizations. Her work so far has focussed on anti-corruption, transparency, governance and business and human rights. In the area of anti-money laundering and anti-corruption, she has consulted for the Senate of Canada, Deloitte, Publish What You Pay Canada, and a number of corporate and NGO clients. She has appeared as an expert witness in her professional capacity before the House of Commons and Senate Finance Committees.

2006 – 2016 Foreign Affairs Canada and Natural Resources Canada.

At NRCan and Foreign Affairs, advised the Government of Canada on issues relating to the extractive sector, anti-corruption standards and international law, including the Corruption of Foreign Public Officials Act (CFPOA), conflict minerals standards, the UN Guiding Principles on Business and Human Rights, the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative, and the Voluntary Principles on Security and Human Rights. Worked extensively and collaboratively in the context of multi-stakeholder initiatives; helped resolve governance issues and build governance capacity in many of these initiatives. Examples of relevant work include:

- Served as Canada's Head of Delegation to the OECD Forum on Responsible Supply Chains (2009-2014). In 2011, elected by a multi-stakeholder working group at the OECD to co-chair the negotiation process of a Conflict Gold Standard, and in 2012, elected to Chair an Interim Governance Group created to help resolve governance issues at the initiative. As Chair, drafted the terms of reference to create a permanent Multi-stakeholder Steering Committee, which was adopted unanimously. Elected to Chair the OECD Forum on Responsible Supply Chains and its multi-stakeholder steering committee 2012-2015.
- Advised the Government of Canada on the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative

(EITI). Drafted the Government of Canada's official legal opinion on governance and legal issues involved in creating an EITI Secretariat/separate legal entity and multistakeholder Board (2008).

- Served in the multi-stakeholder steering committee of the Voluntary Principles on Security and Human Rights Initiative, which includes mining companies and NGOs (2014-2015.)
- Planned, organized and chaired numerous multi-stakeholder consultations and expert meetings, including in 2012 a stock-taking of 10 years of multi-stakeholder initiatives in the extractive sector (EITI, Kimberley Process, Voluntary Principles on Security and Human Rights).
- Served as the Foreign Affairs Legal Bureau lead on the Corruption of Foreign Public
 Officials Act (CFPOA). Worked extensively with the RCMP on enforcement of the
 CFPOA, as well as Canadian stakeholders on corruption issues, including civil society and
 business. Served as Head of the Canadian delegation to the OECD Working Group on
 Bribery (2008-2009), and formally reviewed other nations' foreign bribery laws through
 the OECD peer review process. Developed a corruption policy at Global Affairs with
 regards to mission handling of suspected bribery offences by Canadian companies.
- Government of Canada lead on UN Guiding Principles on Business and Human Rights (2006-2008). Participated at a speaker at numerous multi-stakeholder consultations globally and drafted the Government of Canada's official submission to the UN Special Representative for Business and Human Rights, John Ruggie.

2005 – 2006 Executive Director, Iran Human Rights Documentation Center, New Haven, Connecticut

Overall responsibilities included managing the center's budget, finances, staff, directing the Center's programs. Projects included directing the drafting and publishing of human rights reports on thematic topics; overseeing the development of a secure human rights database which makes available to the public a large collection of human rights-related documents in a searchable format. Also provided some Board development, e.g. helped the Board develop a common mission statement.

2004 – 2005 Student-at-Law, Gowling Lafleur Henderson LLP, Ottawa

Researched legal issues, drafted memos, motions, facta and other court documents. Projects included co-authoring academic articles with two partners, drafting a book chapter, assisting with two commissions of inquiry, work in international trade law.

2003 Law Clerk, Appellate Section, Office of the Prosecutor, Special Court for Sierra Leone

Researched and drafted Prosecution motions, including international law topics on Head of State immunity, criminality of recruiting children, and the applicability of domestic amnesties to international prosecutions.

1999 – 2001 Legislative Assistant, Foreign Affairs and International Trade Canada

Served as Legislative Assistant, Office of the Minister for International Trade, Pierre Pettigrew; and Legislative Assistant, Office of the Minister of Foreign Affairs, Lloyd Axworthy. Tasks included preparing briefing books and briefing Ministers daily prior to Question Period. Responsible for steering Government bills through Parliament, motions, emergency debates, private member's business, and work of the Standing Committees relating to foreign affairs issues.

1996 – 1999 Executive Assistant to Bill Graham, Chair, Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs and International Trade

Principal advisor to MP, including on Standing Committee activities, legislative procedures, and political strategy. Administered Hill and Constituency Office budgets and human resources.

EDUCATION AND MEMBERSHIPS:

Member of the Board of Directors, the Canadian Commercial Corporation (Crown Corporation), appointed July 2019.

Law Society of Upper Canada, Member of the Bar in good standing since 2005.

Member of Legal Committee, Transparency International Canada since 2018.

Juris Doctor (LLB), Faculty of Law, University of Toronto (2004). Winner of Academic Award for finishing Third Place in the class of 180 in graduating year.

Bachelor of Arts (Honours), Trent University (1994). Joint major in Comparative Development Studies and Political Studies.

GUEST LECTURES AND CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS:

- December 2, 2019, **University of Ottawa, Faculty of Law:** Developments in the Business and Human Rights Field
- June 12, 2019, **Carleton University:** Casualty or Catalyst, Gender Equality and the Future of Mining (Event Moderator)
- May 16, 2019, **Transparency International Canada Day of Dialogue**: Beneficial Ownership Transparency and Privacy Concerns under Canadian Law
- May 9, 2018, Canadian Institute 17th Annual Forum on Anti-money Laundering & Financial Crime:

 The Canada Papers? Obscured "True" Ownership and Lessons Learned from Other Jurisdictions

- April 30, 2018, **Canadian corporate counsel association national conference**: *Ethics and the In-house Counsel: What is Your Role In Combatting Labour Abuses?*
- March 14, 2018, **University of Ottawa, Faculty of Law**: Business Law and the Transparency of Beneficial Ownership
- March 27, 2017, **University of Ottawa, Faculty of Law:** Supply Chain Due Diligence: Lessons Learned from Mechanisms to Address Conflict Minerals
- March 22, 2017, **University of Western Ontario, Faculties of Geology, Business and Law:** Supply Chain Due Diligence and Responsible Sourcing of Minerals and Metals
- March 8, 2017, **Ryerson University Business School:** State & Non-state Regulatory Innovations: *Learning from Conflict Minerals*
- December 2016, **Carleton University Canadian Studies Doctoral Program:** Introduction to Transnational Corporations and Human Rights
- November 2016, International Commission of Jurists Conference on Modern Day Slavery: Lessons

 Learned from Supply Chain Due Diligence Mechanisms to Address Conflict Minerals
- November 2016, **Canadian Conference on International Law:** Just and Reasonable Settlements for Transnational Human Rights Abuses
- March 2016, **University of Western Ontario, Faculties of Geology, Business and Law:** Supply Chain Due Diligence and Responsible Sourcing of Minerals and Metals
- February 2016, **University of Ottawa, Faculty of Law:** Supply Chain Due Diligence: Lessons Learned from Mechanisms to Address Conflict Minerals
- November 2015, **Canadian Conference on International Law:** Supply Chain Due Diligence: Lessons Learned from Mechanisms to Address Conflict Minerals
- November 2014, **Canadian Conference on International Law:** Chair, Book Panel Re Governance Gap by Penelope Simons and Audrey Macklin
- June 2014, Partnership Africa Canada: Towards Responsible and Conflict Free Mineral Supply Chains
- March 2013, **Prospectors and Developers Association of Canada Annual Convention:** The Growing Market Demand for Responsibly Produced, Conflict-Free Metals
- May 2012, **Paris, London Bullion Market Association Responsible Gold Forum:** Coordination and Implementation of Key International Initiatives
- May 2012, Paris, OECD Forum on Responsible Mineral Supply Chains: Introduction to the Supplement on Gold